<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="master_schedule.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-model href="master_schedule.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<schedule>
    <week num="1">
        <title>Week 1</title>
        <day d="Monday">
            <date>July 11, 2022</date>
            <syn>>The Institute opens with a high-level view of the types of engagement required by
                a textual editor, beginning (always!) from the research questions and leading to the
                production of an actual edition. In session two we introduce the computational
                pipeline as a way of modeling the development of a digital edition. The afternoon
                sessions ground the morning’s theoretical work with a presentation of the research
                goals and materials to be used in the laboratory edition. We discuss document
                analysis and OCR as first steps in the editorial workflow. The special topic session
                of this first day is reserved for participants to install the software packages
                required to work on the laboratory edition, all of which will be provided by the
                Institute.</syn>
            <slot time="09:00:00">
                <title>Getting started</title>
                <desc>Introductions, research questions, schedules, outcome goals.</desc>
                <act time="15" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Introductions.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Introduce everyone to one another.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="25" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Research questions and choosing our technologies.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Make informed methodological and technical decisions based on our
                            research questions.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="20" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Discuss two-week schedule and day plans.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Set expectations for institute.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Talk_lab">
                    <desc>Review laboratory outcome goals and explore participant goals for their
                        own editions.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Set goals. Practice describing goals.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="10:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="11:00:00">
                <title>The edition as a computational pipeline</title>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>We introduce the computational pipeline as a way of modeling the
                        development of a digital edition.</desc>
                    <outcome/>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Initial stages: TEI XML (base view), exploring with XPath, and exploratory
                        data analysis (EDA).</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Understand base view processing and EDA.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Transformation: how do I transform, what do I transform to? We also
                        introduce the model-view-controller (MVC) architecture we’ll use in app
                        development later on.</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="12:30:00">
                <title>Lunch</title>
                <act time="90">
                    <desc>Lunch</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="14:00:00">
                <title>Selecting your tools and software installation best practices</title>
                <act time="90" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>[Software installation instructions](installs.md).</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="15:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="16:00:00">
                <title>Software installation (continued)</title>
                <act time="60" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Software installation.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Every participant understands our software choice rationale and has
                            installed all required software.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Exploratory data analysis in eXide.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Introduce XQuery with Shakespeare TEI in eXide.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
        <day d="Tuesday">
            <date>July 12, 2022</date>
            <syn>Project management and planning the edition. After the first day’s emphasis on
                theory, model, and method, day two concentrates on baseline technical topics needed
                to translate edition goals into an implementation plan. We begin the day with Agile
                project management, after which the version control system Git, its online
                collaboration environment GitHub, and project file management best practice are
                introduced. In the afternoon the participants apply these best practices while
                setting up the file system in eXist-db. In the special topic session participants
                explore the command line environment they will use to manage files.</syn>
            <slot time="09:00:00">
                <title>Project management</title>
                <desc>Introductions, research questions, schedules, outcome goals.</desc>
                <act time="90" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Project management.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Learn project management basics.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="10:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="11:00:00">
                <title>Git, GitHub, and Markdown</title>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Git: introduce and begin to use version control software.</desc>
                    <outcome/>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>GitHub: code management, issues, projects, and Markdown.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Gain familiarity with the project GitHub space.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>XQuery: introduce FLWOR.</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="12:30:00">
                <title>Lunch</title>
                <act time="90">
                    <desc>Lunch</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="14:00:00">
                <title>File management</title>
                <act time="60" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>File management and command line basics.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Know your machine better.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>XQuery: practice FLWOR.</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="15:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="16:00:00">
                <title>Special topic: Sustainability with Alison Langmead</title>
                <act time="90" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Software installation.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Participants learn to create sustainability plans.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
        <day d="Wednesday">
            <date>July 13, 2022</date>
            <syn>Moving from model to implementation. The third day is devoted to developing the
                digital editing workflow as a computational pipeline. Session one gives a high-level
                overview of data models for documents, such as TEI XML, LMNL, and TAG. In session
                two we discuss applications of the TEI to digital editions. In the afternoon the
                focus remains on TEI, but extends to implementation, as participants perform
                hands-on group markup activities based on the previous day’s document analysis. The
                special topic session, led by guest lecturer Patrick Juola, professor of computer
                science Duquesne University and developer of the open-source JGAAP stylometry
                toolkit, introduces stylometry as an example of integrating statistical description
                and evaluation into the perspectives exposed within an edition.</syn>
            <slot time="09:00:00">
                <title>Command line</title>
                <desc>Practice navigating your file system and using tools at the command line,
                    including Git.</desc>
                <act time="90" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Do command line stuff.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Practice file management at the command line.</goal>
                        <goal>Practice Git at the command line.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>

            </slot>
            <slot time="10:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="11:00:00">
                <title>Modeling the data for the edition</title>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>How do data models and the computational pipeline work together?</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Introduce computational pipelines.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>TEI XML in context: rationales and alternatives.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Make explicit our assumptions about TEI, our data, markup decisions,
                            and edition goals.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Encoding data in TEI XML together in small groups.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Explore how the laboratory edition data might look different with
                            different research questions and markup.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>

            </slot>
            <slot time="12:30:00">
                <title>Lunch</title>
                <act time="90">
                    <desc>Lunch</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="14:00:00">
                <title>XQuery</title>
                <act time="90" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Creating a pipeline with XQuery: you are the controller.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Create our first computational pipeline together.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>

            </slot>
            <slot time="15:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="16:00:00">
                <title>Stylometry</title>
                <act time="90" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Stylometry.</desc>
                    <outcome/>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
        <day d="Thursday">
            <date>July 14, 2022</date>
            <syn>XQuery. Day four reimagines the edition in a research-driven way within a digital
                environment. In session one we guide participants through installing an application
                into eXist-db. In the afternoon, participants use these new skills by developing
                their own XQuery to be implemented later in an eXist-db application framework. The
                final session of the day will focus on collation.</syn>
            <slot time="09:00:00">
                <title>XML databases and indexes</title>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Databases have, at minimum, data and an index. Some apps also have queries
                        and superstructure, which enables content management (CMS).</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Understand the benefits and limitations of XML databases.</goal>
                        <goal>Become familiar with the many different types of indexes one can use
                            in an XML database.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Indexing and profiling. Examine indexes and profiles in Monex.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Understand indexes by running queries with and without indexed
                            data.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Using Lucene indexes. What are facets and fields?</desc>
                </act>

            </slot>
            <slot time="10:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="11:00:00">
                <title>Developing a feature</title>
                <act time="30" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Add your facets and fields to the index and begin querying.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Become familiar with eXist-db index syntax.</goal>
                        <goal>Understand facets and fields.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="60" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Participants work together on preliminary code that they would like to
                        develop into a feature.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Gain experience writing code aligned with research goals.</goal>
                        <goal>Use MVC framework to output "model" data.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="12:30:00">
                <title>Lunch</title>
                <act time="90">
                    <desc>Lunch</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="14:00:00">
                <title>The controller</title>
                <act time="30" type="Discussion">
                    <desc>What is a controller? Why do we need it? What factors determine controller
                        design?</desc>
                </act>
                <act time="15" type="Discussion">
                    <desc>Explore how the out-of-the-box controller works, along with what it can
                        and cannot do.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Prepare to write your own controller.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="45" type="Code_lab">
                    <desc>Write your controller features.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Understand controller writing syntax.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="15:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="16:00:00">
                <title>Collation</title>
                <act time="90" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Collation.</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>


        <day d="Friday">
            <date/>
            <syn>Collaborating on the edition. In session one we introduce the TEI ODD (One Document
                Does it all), a mechanism for documenting customizations to the TEI for
                project-specific purposes. Then, instructors lead small groups in applying ODD
                modeling to the laboratory edition. In session two we introduce GitHub Projects, a
                Kanban-style collaboration tool, and guide participants through debugging and
                resolving merge conflicts in Git. In session three we introduce the use of eXist-db
                as a Content Management System so as to prepare participants for active publication
                development in week two. Guest lecturer Jeffrey Witt, General Editor of the
                Scholastic Commentaries and Texts Archive, closes the day with a special topic
                session on the International Image Interoperability Framework (IIIF), a
                community-focused Linked Open Data (LOD) standard for image sharing.</syn>
            <slot time="09:00:00">
                <title>ODDs and collaborative encoding</title>
                <act time="90" type="Discussion">
                    <desc>Writing the ODD and other mechanisms for document control and
                        documentation.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Enable better collaborative encoding for projects.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>

            </slot>

            <slot time="10:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="10:30:00">
                <title>Using GitHub for project management</title>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Create Kanban boards in GitHub Projects and explore some other software
                        tools available.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Introduce Kanban and other software for task and issue
                            management.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Discussion">
                    <desc>Issues and pull requests</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Create pull requests on the institute repositories.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
                <act time="30" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Create merge conflicts on purpose to gain familiarity with resolving them
                        (without being thrown into a VIM blackhole).</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Become comfortable with merge conflicts and using Git.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="12:30:00">
                <title>Lunch</title>
                <act time="90">
                    <desc>Lunch</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="14:00:00">
                <title>Search functionality</title>
                <act time="90" type="Presentation">
                    <desc>Together as a group, we deconstruct and rewrite the app's search
                        functionality.</desc>
                    <outcome>
                        <goal>Understand the development algorithm for creating advanced
                            features.</goal>
                        <goal>Use several advanced features in eXist-db to support research
                            outcomes.</goal>
                    </outcome>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="15:30:00">
                <title>Coffee break</title>
                <act time="30">
                    <desc>Coffee break</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
            <slot time="16:00:00">
                <title>International Image Interoperability Framework (IIIF) and Linked Open Data (LOD)</title>
                <act time="90">
                    <desc>Jeffrey Witt presents on IIIF.</desc>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
    </week>
  <week num="2">
        <title>Week 2</title>
        <day d="Monday">
            <date>July 18, 2022</date>
            <syn>Preparing for deployment. In week two, participants prepare the laboratory edition
                for publication, exposing the functionalities of querying, filtering, analyzing, and
                transforming textual data. In session one, we take stock of the progress of our
                collaborative edition and the work plan for completion. In session two we survey
                publication options like TEI Publisher and CETEIcean with comparative reference to
                GitHub Pages and the laboratory edition eXist-db implementation. In the afternoon,
                participants practice transformations with XML technologies, focusing on control
                over design and functionality. The day’s special topic session will be a
                presentation on user experience and design by guest lecturer Shea Higgins.</syn>
            <slot time="">
                <title/>
                <act time="">
                    <desc/>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
      <!--  
        <day d="Tuesday">
            <date>July 19, 2022</date>
            <syn>Implementing publication strategies.** The morning is devoted to HTML and CSS,
                which constitute the “view” aspect of the laboratory edition’s MVC architecture. In
                session two, participants return to the application in eXist-db and gain experience
                with application requirements. In the afternoon, participants deploy the first-draft
                edition within eXist-db with a session that implements the model, view, and
                controller together. To wrap up the day, we'll discuss unit testing and writing
                functions.</syn>
            <slot time="">
                <title/>
                <act time="">
                    <desc/>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
        <day d="Wednesday">
            <date>July 20, 2022</date>
            <syn>Visualization and interactivity. On day three participants learn to communicate
                information about data through interactive graphs and charts. In session one we
                introduce Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG), an XML technology that allows users to
                create data-driven charts and graphs with XQuery. In session two we introduce
                JavaScript, which enables the user to modify the view within the browser. The
                afternoon’s small-group hands-on session, with all instructors providing guidance,
                inte- grates these techniques into the edition for publication, as participants
                develop responsive, user-oriented visualizations exported and transformed from the
                laboratory edition data. Guest lecturer Elisa Beshero-Bondar, Professor of Digital
                Humanities at Penn State Erie, The Behrend College and Director of Digital Mitford,
                will teach the first part of a special topic session on network analysis with
                text.</syn>
            <slot time="">
                <title/>
                <act time="">
                    <desc/>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
        <day d="Thursday">
            <date>July 21, 2022</date>
            <syn>Data access and APIs.** The morning sessions focus on accommodating both the
                developer-user and the eventual end-user. First, participants learn to collaborate
                over GitHub through issues and pull requests. In the second session we introduce
                Application Programming Interfaces (APIs). The afternoon’s session allows
                participants to develop a collaborative starter API for the laboratory edition,
                which we will be able to publish and use that day. The final session is reserved for
                review and catch-up.</syn>
            <slot time="">
                <title/>
                <act time="">
                    <desc/>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>
        <day d="Friday">
            <date/>
            <syn>Finishing up. In the first session, participants will discuss and reflect upon the
                modeling choices made in development of the laboratory edition. These choices
                influence every part of the edition workflow, which participants will explore as
                they present on the interfaces, visualizations, and features they developed as part
                of their hands-on sessions, as well as their plans to apply their new skills to
                their own edition work. Finally, we survey resources for further education, and also
                allocate one-on-one time with instructors for participants to discuss application of
                what they have learned and developed in the Institute into their own editions.</syn>
            <slot time="">
                <title/>
                <act time="">
                    <desc/>
                </act>
            </slot>
        </day>-->
    </week>

</schedule>
